A Guide to the Frank Harris Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7453-b
Frank Harris Collection 1894-1924
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7453-b
40 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 Nov 5
Item Listing
- Letters
  - Frank Harris to Kineton Parker, 1894 Dec 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for review of stories; asks if he would like to review any books at present.]
  - Frank Harris to Miss Schuster, 1898 Apr 5; ALS, 1 p.
    [Relishes her sympathetic letter; discusses his articles on Shakespeare; warns that future articles will show the unpleasant, "dark shadows" of Shakespeare's life; wishes for more frequent correspondence.]
  - Frank Harris to "Dear Madam", 1906 Feb 8; TLS, 1 p.
    [Will now accept previously rejected terms offered by [Charles] Frohman for a production of "Mr. and Mrs. Daventry"; suggests concluding the arrangement through Addison Bright. ] [w/ec]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1908 Apr 25; TLS, 1 p.
    [Offers for publication his first long novel, "an implicit defence of the rebels against society."]
  - Frank Harris to "Dear Sir", 1908 Nov 12; TLS, 2 p.
    [Responds to request for his portrait by enclosing a photograph; believes reviewers misread
    The Bomb
    mentions several books and plays that lack an audience; hopes a daring publisher will produce them someday.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, [1914] Aug 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Two books
    The Veils of Isis
    and a novel to be titled either
    Morning
    or
    Love in Youth
    will be published in the U.S. soon; wishes to sell the English rights; copies are available from Normaford Burnett; outlines possible improvements. Solicits opinion of
    Great Days
    mentions economic hardships and comments on the surprising quiet of " Paris in siege time."]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Aug 9; ALS, 4 p.
    [Sends galley proofs of improved short stories included in a collection entitled either
    The Yellow Ticket
    discusses financial concerns resulting from the war; mentions
    Memorial Edition
    of Shakespeare to be published by Hearst; predicts that a short war with social revolution in Berlin might end the Hohenzollern dynasty.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Aug 15; ALS, 3 p.
    [Claims articles in the
    Daily Sketch
    misrepresented him; discusses stories to be included in
    describes
    The Memorial Edition of Shakespeare
    which he hopes Hearst will publish in 1916; this edition will include proof that two plays were written by Shakespeare; mentions work on
    hopes to leave France for New York; says Normaford Burnett has a corrected copy of "The Ugly Duckling."]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Aug 22; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sold rights to publish
    in Great Britain, the colonies, and India; hopes to leave Paris for the front; notes that life in Paris is in "suspended animation"; agrees
    The Yellow Room
    is best title; will amend story and terms of agreement if necessary; inquires about publication date and possibility of book on the war; mentions Davidson piece in
    Contemporary Portraits
    . ]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, [1914 Aug] 28; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for payment; agrees to contract changes; suggests possibility of doing
    Memorial Edition of Shakespeare
    in 1916; believes that "small men" such as Deschanel, Clemenceau, Millerand, Joffre, Pall, Kitchener, and Churchill are without a touch of greatness; will observe Joffre "at work"; mentions new story for
    expects that war will be a long one, barring a revolution in Germany; requests help getting position as correspondent for English or American newspaper.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Oct 9; TLS, 1 p.
    [Sends corrected proofs and changed order of stories; needs to work on
    hopes to do so on ship to New York; mentions lack of communication about money.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Oct 15; ALS, 1 p.
    [Will send proofs; cannot write story on ship because of seasickness; will try in New York; will send power of attorney someday.] (RMS Olympic stationery)
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Nov 8; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends corrected
    discusses unsuccessful attempts to publish war articles in New York, and a successful lecture at the Arts Club; believes the Ponds Agency will offer him further opportunities to lecture; mentions financial situation, article on "American Opinion," and British failures of statesmanship.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1914 Dec 8; TL, 1 p.
    [Regrets early publication of
    will visit Douglas Doty, but feels American editors prefer bad work over good; requests twelve copies of
    be sent in care of Temple Scott and one to John F. Harris, head of
    Cambridge Review
    writing book on the war with an anti-British theme.] (initialed by WGD)
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1915 Jan 11; TLS, 2 p.
    [Complains of errors in the [British] edition of
    doubts Richards has "pluck" to publish his controversial, pro-German book on the war; admits that moderating comments on Justice Horridge in the book might be reasonable.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1915 Apr 16; TLS, 3 p.
    [Sends
    England or Germany
    , hoping he will publish it with the usual commission; asks his opinion of the book; declares book is not libelous, but Judge Horridge's name may be omitted; complains about Arnold Benett's criticism of his
    Sun
    articles; mentions lecture tour, publication of
    by Methuen. Declares success of lecture tour in the West; says wife will travel to England; hopes his American nationality will be publicized by Richards in order to deflect criticism in
    Truth
    and
    The Globe
    that he is a traitor; predicts German victory.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1916 Mar 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Hopes letter reaches Frank Palmer; mentions copyrights on
    The Man Shakespeare
    ,
    Shakespeare and His Loves
    , and his plan to publish a complete edition of his own works; requests copy of George Morris' book on Jesus; mentions sales of
    and forthcoming works
    Oscar Wilde: His Life and Confessions
    rejoices that he is feeling creative again; hopes their friendship will not be affected by differences of opinion.]
  - Frank Harris to Wilbur Underwood, 1916 Oct 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Discusses Wilde book and shares views on his life; welcomes a visit when he is in New York when they can talk about his Mirbeau translation.]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1917 Mar 30; TLS, 1 p.
    [Requests books which he has seen in
    The Nation
    The Outlook
  - Frank Harris to W. R. Weber, 1919 Feb 6; TLS, 1 p.
    [Wishes he were in Bernkastel, Germany; sends six copies of
    Pearson's
    and his first book of short stories; questions states of destitution in Northern France and Germany; requests a long letter.]
  - Frank Harris to W. R. Weber, 1919 Mar 27; TLS, 1 p. w/env
    [Indicates he may publish part of Weber's letter; requests an account of his experiences which might be used as an article; hopes to meet him on his return; urges him to promote
    among his comrades.]
  - Frank Harris to W. R. Weber, 1919 Apr 25; TLS, 2 p.
    [Comments on the state of Europe, the transfer of territories including the Saar valley and Metz, political greed, and his despair for the future; in AN at bottom, requests a detailed account of the correspondent's experiences, specifically about conditions in Germany. ]
  - Frank Harris to Grant Richards, 1919 Nov 8; TLS, 2 p.
    [Introduces [Claude] McKay whose poems he admires; suggests they are more likely to be published in book form in England as he is Jamaican; has sent a letter to [George Bernard] Shaw; would like McKay to meet either Siegfried Sassoon or the Sitwells or Robert Nichols. ]
  - Frank Harris to Mr. Smart, 1924 Feb 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Describes his own reaction to
    My Life and Loves
    extols its honesty; outlines second volume of autobiography to be published soon which includes "sex stories" of his contemporaries; expects it will be confiscated; discusses price of first volume; will have one sent by friends; mentions financial difficulties because of resentment of his pacifism in the U.S.A.; expects to "triumph" eventually.]
  - Frank Harris to [Adelia] Schuster, 1924 Sep 18; ALS, 2 p.
    [Describes the year's literary production, the fourth volume of
    Undreamed of Shores
    published by Grant Richards; solicits her opinion of them; inquires about the copies of
    The Life and Confessions of Oscar Wilde
    he had sent and whether they contained Bernard Shaw's "Memoirs of Oscar Wilde"; describes the second volume of
    My Life [and Loves]
    and the people portrayed in it; believes its honesty is a return to Ben Jonson and William Shakespeare. ]
  - Frank Harris to Baroness d'Erlanger, 1924 Sep 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Inquires if the copy of
    ordered before the war was received because he discovered a subscriber who had not received his; mentions Bernard Shaw's praise for the book and the inclusion of his "Memoirs of Oscar Wilde" in later editions.]
  - Frank Harris to Mr. Townsend, 1924 Oct 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Gives wholesale and retail prices of volumes one and two of
    describes volume two as his best book; hopes to avoid "US smut-hounds" by binding it in plain paper; uncertain that
    Ulysses
    will get through customs, but gives the name and address of its publisher.]
  - Nellie Harris to Grant Richards, n.y. Oct 14; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends enclosure at Frank Harris's request; forwards packet to him in U.S.; will deliver agreement made with Palmer for the Shakespeare. ]
  - Frank Harris to [Adelia] Schuster, Tues morning; ALS, 3 p.
    [Praises her love of truth but disagrees with her opinion about the "Marconi speculations"; describes the corruption of Lloyd George and Rufus Isaacs; refers her to piece in
    The National Review
    on the matter; criticizes his own writing style used in an article on Theodore Dreiser in
    The Academy
    feels he should have rewritten it; requests visit to read corrected version of
    will then begin work on
- Photograph
  - Photograph by E. O. Hoppe of Frank Harris, Winter 1922-23; Photograph
- Miscellaneous
  - Letter to the editor of The Sun regarding Harris' opinion of France, 1915 Mar 7; Newspaper clipping